Finding Aid for College of Pharmacy (University of Michigan) records, 1864-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
College of Pharmacy (University of Michigan) records 1864-2010 1940-2000
University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.
Background files with historical information and biographical data on college deans and faculty; chronological files, 1868-1994, including faculty and executive committee minutes, annual reports, and subject files, largely of deans Howard Lewis, Charles H. Stocking, Thomas D. Rowe, and Ara G. Paul; records of Prescott Club, organization of pharmacy students; and photographs.
87105 Bimu C81 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
37 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
20.3 MB online
The records have been received in accessions from the College of Pharmacy (donor no. 3112 ) since 1955.
The collection is open for research with the exception of files personnel and student record related material which are closed in accordance with university policy and applicable law. Restricted files in the College of Pharmacy records include:
Personnel related records, located in box 35-37
Student related records, located in box 17.
Executive Committee minutes, which include faculty personnel records, are closed for thirty years from date of creation. Located in Box 18-34
The College of Pharmacy dates from the appointment of Douglass Houghton in 1839 as professor of Geology, Mineralogy, and "with the subjects of Chemistry and Pharmacy, till Regents take further order in relation thereto." In 1844, Houghton was joined by his cousin Silas Hamilton Douglass who was charged with assisting in the instruction of chemistry and related sciences. Although it does not appear that Douglass taught any pharmacy courses, it was under his direction in 1860 that the first pharmacy laboratory course was offered by an assistant, Alfred DuBois. Upon DuBois' departure from the university in 1863, the regents appointed two student assistants to cover DuBois' responsibilities, Henry S. Cheever and Albert B. Prescott. Prescott completed his academic degree in 1864, served for a year in the U.S. Army, and returned to the University as an assistant professor of chemistry. In 1868, the regents established "Pharmaceutical Chemistry" as a degree-granting program within the Department of Literature, Science, and Arts. The program expanded again, in 1876 to become the School of Pharmacy with Prescott as dean. (The name was changed to the College of Pharmacy in 1915, in accordance with university policy adopted at that time.)
Under Prescott's leadership the curriculum was set at a year-and-a-half program leading to a pharmaceutical chemistry degree. Recognition of the program by the American Pharmaceutical Association was initially refused in 1871 because the Michigan format emphasized basic sciences instead of the apprenticeship system. By 1885, however, several major universities had copied the Michigan program and accreditation followed as the value of the scientific approach was recognized. A graduate studies program had been added in 1882 and in 1895 a bachelor of sciences degree was initiated to supplement the basic undergraduate program.
Upon the death of Dr. Prescott in 1905, the deanship was assumed by Julius O. Schlotterbeck, who served for twelve years and ushered in an era of expanded student services and activities. Field trips to pharmaceutical firms such as Upjohn Company, and Parke-Davis, and Company became annual activities. Student financial support was provided through the Prescott Memorial Loan Fund beginning in 1906. Two student societies were formed in 1908 to encourage scholarship and social interaction. The Aristolochite Society was formed as a local honors organization for exceptional pharmacy students. In 1922, it became the Alpha chapter of the Rho Chi (RX) Society. The Prescott Club, which was open to all pharmacy students, sponsored lectures and social activities. In 1946 the Prescott Club became the A.B. Prescott Student Chapter, American Pharmaceutical Association.
In 1920, after a three-year period in which the college was led by Alviso B. Stevens (1917-1919) and Henry Kraemer (1919-1920), Edward H. Kraus began a fourteen-year tenure as dean. He initiated the doctoral program in pharmacy and encouraged corporate-sponsored fellowships for graduate students. Kraus gave Professor Frederick F. Blicke responsibility for training graduate students in synthetic organic pharmaceutical chemistry. Blicke became a recognized leader in this field and was mentor to dozens of doctoral candidates.
Howard B. Lewis served as dean of the College of Pharmacy from 1933 to 1947, and steered the school through the difficult years of the Great Depression and World War II. From a low point of only forty four students in February 1933, Lewis was able to increase enrollment to seventy two students in March, 1935. Thereafter, the College of Pharmacy continued to grow until the outbreak of war in 1941-1942. As a result of the military draft and accelerated programs, the enrollment dropped to a low of thirty one students in May 1944. During the war years, the College of Pharmacy participated in a Navy training program and in two research projects concerning synthetic and "sulfa" drugs.
The strengthening of community relations can be traced to Dr. Lewis' tenure. The "Annual Pharmacy Lectures" began in 1932. Thereafter, the college annually sponsored a day when pharmacists from throughout the state gathered to hear papers on a variety of pharmacy topics. With Lewis' support the lectures became an important link between the university and the statewide community. In 1937, the college began to broadcast pharmacy lectures of general interest over Ann Arbor and Detroit radio stations. The programs covered a diverse spectrum of subjects ranging from "Food and Drug Legislation" to "Chewing Gum." An extension course in pharmacy was offered for the first time in 1941, on a co-operative basis by the University of Michigan, the Michigan State Pharmacy Association, and the State Board of Control for Vocational Education. The course was conducted in Ann Arbor by a local retail pharmacist and enrolled 110 practicing pharmacists before the war interrupted the program.
Dean Lewis resigned in 1947 and was succeeded by Charles H. Stocking, a popular faculty member and secretary of the College of Pharmacy. A postwar resurgence of students saw enrollment double during the late 1940s. Demand for pharmacists far exceeded the supply and several additional faculty members were hired to meet the increased demands placed upon the college. Additional room for both students and faculty was provided for the college when an addition was completed to the Chemistry Building.
In 1951, Dean Stocking retired and was succeeded by Thomas D. Rowe, former dean of the Rutgers University College of Pharmacy. During Rowe's term (1951-1975) chemical and biochemical course work was strengthened and in 1960 the undergraduate program was lengthened to five years. In graduate work, a new Doctor of Pharmacy program was instituted to replace several masters-level programs. A significant site expansion of the college occurred in 1960 when the Pharmacy Research Building was completed. In addition, renovations in the C.C. Little Building provided the space for laboratories, classrooms, and offices necessary for the increased size and scope of the College.
Upon Dean Rowe's retirement in 1975, Ara G. Paul was named dean of the college. During the initial years of Paul's deanship extensive evaluation was undertaken in order to position the college for optimal growth through the end of the century. Among the significant curricular changes undertaken during the period 1975-1988 were:
The implementation of one integrated curriculum, to be taken by all students. (Previously, several curricula had been available.)
The termination of the B.S. Pharmacy degree in 1984.
The standardization of the internships program.
The introduction of an accelerated Ph.D. program for highly motivated students.
Ara Paul retired as dean in December 1995. He was succeeded by James W. Richards. Richards initially served as interim dean and was elected to a two-year term as dean on July 1, 1996. George L. Kenyon became dean in 1998 and served until 2004, when Frank Ascione was appointed to a five-year term. In 2009, Ascione was appointed to a second five-year term. One of the more notable developments during Ascione's tenure was the university's acquisition of the former Pfizer Research and Development facility (renamed North Campus Research Complex) in 2009, which enabled a variety of new research and educational opportunities for the college. The college hired many former Pfizer scientists to lead research programs.
For current academic program information see the College of Pharmacy website located at http://www.umich.edu/~pharmacy/.
Deans of the College of Pharmacy
1876-1905 Albert B. Prescott
1905-1917 Julius O. Schlotterbeck
1917-1919 Alviso B. Stevens
1919-1920 Henry Kraemer
1920-1933 Edward Krause
1933-1947 Howard B. Lewis
1947-1951 Charles H. Stocking
1951-1975 Thomas D. Rowe
1975-1995 Ara Paul
1995-1998 James W. Richards
1998-2004 George L. Kenyon
2004- Frank J. Ascione
The College of Pharmacy records (37 linear feet) cover the years 1864-2003, but primarily document the years after 1939. Series include: Background Files, Chronological Files, Photograph / Visual Material Files, Topical Files, Executive Committee, Adjunct and Clinical Faculty Appointments, and Website.
The records were received in a number of accessions beginning in 1955. Additions were received in 1992 (Topical files, 1953-1989), 1995 (Topical files 1972-1992 and Executive Committee files), 2000 (Topical files and Executive Committee), and 2004 (Topical files and Executive Committee) and 2008-2011 (Topical files and Executive Committee). The description of the records in part reflects these accessions.
The records accessioned before 1992 (8.7 linear feet) have been divided into three series: Background Files, Chronological Files, and Photograph / Visual Material Files
The 2000 accession includes additions to the Executive Committee Series (1.5 linear feet, 1980-1994) and Topical Files series (5.5 linear feet, 1963-1998). The 2004 accession includes additions to the Executive Committee series (2 linear feet, 1993 -- 1998) and the Topical Files series (2 linear feet, 1971 -- 1999, scattered).
Subjects:
Pharmacy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pharmacy--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Prescott Club (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Lewis, Howard Bishop, 1887-1954.; Paul, Ara G. (Ara Garo), 1929-; Rowe, Thomas Dudley, 1910-; Stocking, Charles Howard, 1882-1958.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Drugstores--Michigan.; Laboratories.; Pharmacies--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Background Files
  The Background Files (.5 linear feet) contain historical and biographical material. The "History" and "Historical Marker" folders contain a variety of essays concerning the history and the historical significance of the College of Pharmacy. Included is a report prepared in 1971 which describes many of the activities of Dean Rowe's tenure. Other files contain biographies, resumes, and lectures relating to the careers of deans and faculty members.
  - History (Box 1)
  - Historical Marker (Box 1)
  - Deans and Faculty Members
    - Blicke, F.F (Box 1)
    - Edmunds, Charles W (Box 1)
    - Glover, Clifford C (Box 1)
    - Kraemer, Henry (Box 1)
    - Kraus, Edward H (Box 1)
    - Paul, Ara G (Box 1)
    - Prescott, Albert B (Box 1)
    - Rowe, Tom D
      - biographical (Box 1)
      - speeches (Box 1)
    - Schlotterbeck, Julius O (Box 1)
    - Stevens, Alviso, B (Box 1)
    - Stocking, Charles H (Box 1)
- Chronological Files 1868-1989
  The Chronological Files are arranged in two subseries: 1868-1939 and 1940-1989.
  - 1868-1939
    The Chronological Files, 1868-1939, (8 linear feet) are arranged by year(s), and within year(s), alphabetically by topic. There are twenty-four folders (.5 linear feet) which contain scattered materials from the pre-1940 years. They have been grouped under the heading 1868-1939. The years to which each of the folders pertain are noted with the folder headings in the contents list. The materials from the early years include complete faculty meeting minutes, budget summaries, radio broadcast transcripts, material from the Prescott Club, and a ten-year report for the years 1909-1919.
    - Accreditation 1927-1928 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report 1909-1910, 1919-1920, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Budget 1910-1920, 1917-1918, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1917-1918 (Box 1)
    - Curriculum 1920s (Box 1)
    - Enrollment Statistics 1914-1939, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Facilities 1904 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Meeting Minutes 1868-1939, 2 volumes; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Fiftieth Anniversary Reunion 1918-1919 (Box 1)
    - Laboratory Notices 1875 (Box 1)
    - Noyes, LaVerne Scholarships 1937-1938 (Box 1)
    - Prescott Club
      - Account Book 1915-1933 (Box 1)
      - Minutes Book 1915-1933 (Box 1)
      - Scrapbook, 1908-? (Box 11)
    - Prescott Loan Fund 1908-1910 (Box 1)
    - Radio Programs 1937-1939 (Box 1)
    - Rho Chi Pharmacy Society 1922-1932 (Box 1)
    - Ten Year Report 1909-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1989
    Chronological Files (1940-1989), (7.5 linear feet) are arranged by academic year. Included among the materials are an almost complete set of faculty minutes for the entire period and a fairly complete run of executive committee minutes for the years 1967-1986. There are extensive budget files, and accreditation files often contain information on important curricular and faculty changes.
    - 1941-1942
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Prescott Loan Fund (Box 2)
      - Selective Service (Box 2)
      - Helfman, (Harry) Scholarship (Box 2)
      - Japanese-American Students (Box 2)
      - Radio Programs (Box 2)
      - Reunion (Class of 1918) (Box 2)
      - Vandenberg, Arthur H., correspondence (Box 2)
      - War Emergency Measures (Box 2)
    - 1943-1944
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 2)
      - Japanese-American Students (Box 2)
      - Reunion (Class of 1919) (Box 2)
    - 1944-1945
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Curriculum (Box 2)
      - Japanese-American Students (Box 2)
      - Radio Programs (Box 2)
    - 1945-1946
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 2)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 2)
      - Radio Programs (Box 2)
      - War Transition Notice (Box 2)
    - 1946-1947
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Veterans) (Box 2)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 2)
      - Placement Survey (Box 2)
      - Radio Programs (Box 2)
    - 1947-1948
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Committee to End Discrimination (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - 1948-1949
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 2)
      - Facilities (Box 2)
      - Zetalethian Society (Box 2)
    - 1949-1950
      - Accreditation (Box 2)
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
    - 1950-1951
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 2)
    - 1951-1952
      - Admissions (Box 2)
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Curriculum (Box 2)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 2)
      - Field Trip (Box 2)
      - Personnel (Box 2)
      - 75th Anniversary-Pharmacy School (Box 2)
      - University Hospital Collaboration (Box 2)
    - 1952-1953
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 2)
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Curriculum (Box 2)
      - Development Council Proposal (Box 2)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 2)
      - Facilities (Box 2)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 2)
      - Field trip (Box 2)
      - Reunion (Class of 1903) (Box 2)
      - Summer Seminar (Box 2)
      - Teachers' Seminar (Box 2)
    - 1953-1954
      - Alexander, (John B.) Scholarship (Box 2)
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 2)
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Curriculum (Box 2)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 2)
      - Facilities (Box 2)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 2)
      - Grants (Box 2)
      - Hazeltine & Perkins Scholarship (Box 2)
      - Recruiting (Box 2)
      - Research (Box 2)
      - Reunions, (Classes of '24,'29,'34,'39,'49) (Box 2)
      - Status Reports (Box 2)
      - Summer Program (Box 2)
    - 1954-1955
      - A.P.A. Student Organization (Box 2)
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Curriculum (Box 2)
      - Emanuel, (J.E.) Scholarships (Box 2)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 2)
      - Facilities (Box 2)
      - Graduate Training Report (Box 2)
      - Pharmacy Student Council (Box 2)
      - Pharmacy Study Group (Box 2)
      - Pharmacognosy (Box 2)
      - Research in Progress (Box 2)
      - Senior Seminar (Box 2)
      - Whitehall Pharmacals Co. Fellowship (Box 2)
    - 1955-1956
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 2)
      - Annual Report (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Curriculum (Box 2)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 2)
      - Facilities (Box 2)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 2)
      - Graduate Program (Box 2)
      - Health Service-Pharmacy Internship (Box 2)
      - Hospital Pharmacy (Box 2)
      - Human Resources Report (Box 2)
    - 1956-1957
      - Admissions (Box 3)
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 3)
      - Annual Report (Box 3)
      - Budget (Box 3)
      - Curriculum (Box 3)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 3)
      - Facilities (Box 3)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
      - Hospital Pharmacy Survey (Box 3)
      - Parke, Davis and Co. Research Facility (Box 3)
      - Personnel (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Student Council (Box 3)
      - Project Status Reports (Box 3)
    - 1957-1958
      - Accreditation Status Report (Box 3)
      - Admissions (Box 3)
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 3)
      - Annual Report (Box 3)
      - Budget (Box 3)
      - Budget Requests (Box 3)
      - Facilities (Box 3)
      - Facility Proposal (Box 3)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
      - Personnel (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Student Council (Box 3)
      - Policy Code (Box 3)
      - Research Proposal (Box 3)
    - 1958-1959
      - Admission (Box 3)
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 3)
      - Army Pharmacy Program (Box 3)
      - Budget (Box 3)
      - Budget, Project Requests (Box 3)
      - Conference Center Proposal (Box 3)
      - Curriculum (Box 3)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 3)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
      - Fund-Raising; New Facility (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Day (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Student Council (Box 3)
      - Recruiting (Box 3)
      - Research Publication Report (Box 3)
      - Safety Issues (Box 3)
    - 1959-1960
      - Alumni Letter (Box 3)
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 3)
      - Annual Report (Box 3)
      - Curriculum (Box 3)
      - Doctor of Pharmacy Program (Box 3)
      - Facilities: New Pharmacy Bldg (Box 3)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
      - Fund-Raising (Box 3)
      - Graduate Program (Box 3)
      - Grant Requests (Box 3)
      - Parke, Davis, and Co. Research Facility (Box 3)
      - Pharmaceuticals Center (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Day (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Student Council (Box 3)
      - Pharmacognosy Program (Box 3)
      - Research Royalties (Box 3)
    - 1960-1961
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 3)
      - Army Pharmacy Program (Box 3)
      - Budget, Project Requests (Box 3)
      - Cancer Research (Box 3)
      - Curriculum (Box 3)
      - Facilities, Pharmacy Research Bldg (Box 3)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Student Council (Box 3)
    - 1961-1962
      - Annual Report (Box 3)
      - Curriculum (Box 3)
      - Curriculum Proposal (Box 3)
      - Facilities, Pharmacy Research Bldg (Box 3)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
      - Fees (Box 3)
      - Pfieffer Foundation Request (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Schools Survey (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Student Council (Box 3)
      - Research Proposals (Box 3)
    - 1962-1963
      - Budget (Box 3)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
      - Pharmacy Student Council (Box 3)
    - 1963-1964
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
    - 1964-1965
      - Enrollment Study (Box 3)
      - Facilities (Box 3)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 3)
    - 1965-1966
      - Drug Science Seminar (Box 4)
      - Enrollment Projections (Box 4)
      - Facilities (Box 4)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 4)
      - Personnel (Box 4)
      - Research Projects (Box 4)
    - 1966-1967
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 4)
      - Facilities (Box 4)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 4)
      - General Research Support Awards (Box 4)
      - Pharmacy-Medical-Nursing Conference (Box 4)
      - University Sesquicentennial Activity (Box 4)
    - 1967-1968
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 4)
      - Administrative Staff (Box 4)
      - Curriculum Committee (Box 4)
      - Drug Science Seminar (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 4)
      - Faculty Issues (Box 4)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 4)
      - General Research Support Awards (Box 4)
      - Health Services Study Committee (Box 4)
      - Status Report (magazine article) (Box 4)
      - Self Study (Box 4)
    - 1968-1969
      - Annual Report (Box 4)
      - Drug Science Seminar (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 4)
      - Facilities (Box 4)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 4)
      - General Research Support Awards (Box 4)
      - Pharmacy Management Seminar (Box 4)
    - 1969-1970
      - Annual Pharmacy Lectures (Box 4)
      - Annual Report (Box 4)
      - Dean's Advisory Committee (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 4)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 4)
      - General Research Support Awards (Box 4)
      - Minority Recruiting (Box 4)
    - 1970-1971
      - Affirmative Action for Women (Box 4)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 4)
    - 1970-1971
      - Executive Committee (Box 4)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 4)
      - General Research Support Awards (Box 4)
      - University Hospital Pharmacy Proposal (Box 4)
    - 1971-1972
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 4)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 4)
      - General Research Support Grants (Box 4)
    - 1972-1973
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 4)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 4)
    - 1973-1974
      - Annual Report (Box 4)
      - Curriculum (Box 4)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 4)
      - Faculty By-Laws (Box 4)
    - 1974-1975
      - Annual Report (Box 5)
      - Enrollment Statistics (Box 5)
      - Evaluations and Visitations (Box 5)
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 5)
    - 1975-1976
      - Accreditation (Box 5)
      - Annual Report (Box 5)
      - Budget (Box 5)
      - Clinical Pharmacy Lab Proposal (Box 5)
      - College of Pharmacy Centennial (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, External (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, University (Box 5)
      - Curriculum (Box 5)
      - Evaluation and Planning (Box 5)
      - Evaluation of Pharmacy Program (Box 5)
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 5)
      - Faculty Minutes (Box 5)
      - Graduate Affairs & Research Committee (Box 5)
      - Health Services Research Grant (Box 5)
      - Medicinal Chemistry Proposal (Box 5)
      - Minority Recruiting (Box 5)
      - Status Report, College of Pharmacy (Box 5)
    - 1976-1977
      - Accreditation (Box 5)
      - Annual Report (Box 5)
      - Budget (Box 5)
      - Community Practice Grant (Box 5)
      - Correspondence (Internal and External), 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Curriculum (Box 5)
      - Evaluation of Program (Box 5)
      - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 5)